Guide to the Marc Crawford and Abby London Crawford Photo Collection ALBA.PHOTO.186
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Marc Crawford and Abby London Crawford Photographs
1987-1998
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Crawford, Marc
Crawford, Abby London
ALBA.PHOTO.186
2.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
Marc Crawford, a journalist, civil rights activist and university teacher, co-authored a pictorial history of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. His wife, Abby London Crawford, a teacher and photographer, accompanied him to veterans' reunions and related events, both in the U.S. and Spain. The collection contains Abby Crawford's photographs of these events, as well as a few related images by other photographers.
Approximately 1,980 4 x 6 inch Color Photographs and four 8 x 10 inch Black and White Photographs; Approximately 1,980 Color Negatives
Provenance
The Crawford Photograph Collection was donated to New York University in 2002.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Abby London Crawford, the widow of Marc Crawford, is a teacher and an accomplished photographer, whose work has appeared in the national and radical press. Marc Crawford, a journalist, civil rights activists and university teacher, collaborated with William Loren Katz on The Lincoln Brigade: A Picture History (Atheneum, 1989). In the course of preparing that book, and for several years afterward, Marc and Abby Crawford attended veterans' gatherings in the U.S. and Spain, and she documented those events in hundreds of photographs. She had been specially invited by the veterans to photograph their 1986 reunion for a planned Brigade history for young people, a project that was eventually transformed, with the enthusiastic support of Brigade Commander, Steve Nelson, into the Crawford-Katz pictorial history. After Marc Crawford's death in 1996, Abby Crawford continued to be involved with the Lincoln veterans, and to record their recent history in photographs.
After many years as a classroom teacher, Abby Crawford developed a special Music Appreciation/Choral Singing/Language Arts program at the Ella Baker School. With her friend Frances Patai, a writer who documented women's participation in the volunteer medical services during the Spanish Civil War, she sang in the New York City Labor Chorus.
Scope and Content Note
The Crawford Photograph Collection includes approximately 1,980 color prints and four black and white prints. The color prints are 4 x 6 inches and the black and white prints are 8 x 10 inches.The negatives are stored separately from the prints, in Box 2.
Series I: The approximately 1,980 color prints are in files arranged alphabetically by topic. Most were taken by Abby London Crawford while attending special events organized by the Lincoln Brigade veterans in Spain and the United States. The bulk of the collection consists of photographs of these events; there is also a small assortment of portraits including images of Marc Crawford, Steve Nelson and James Yates. There are a few images taken in Spain by Eric Levenson and four prints by Barbara Smith of a protest outside the offices of the Village Voice newspaper. VALB members were protesting an article by Paul Berman in which veteran William Herrick made some controversial statements about brigade history.
Series II: Negatives in files arranged alphabetically by topic. The approximately 1,980 negatives are contained in a separate box from the photographs. Most of the color negatives have matching prints. There are no negatives for the 8 x 10 black and white prints.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by topic in both the Prints and Negatives series.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
Missing Title
I: Prints
II: Negatives
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Marc Crawford and Abby London Crawford Papers, ALBA 186.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Negatives (photographic); Black-and-white photographs.; Seville (Spain); Barcelona (Spain); Madrid (Spain); Crawford, Abby London; Johnson, Howard "Stretch"; Yates, James, 1906-; Crawford, Marc; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Nelson, Steve, 1903-1993; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion
- Series I: Photographs
  - Book on Display (The Lincoln Brigade: A Picture History), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - British Battalion, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Crawford, Marc (with Steve Nelson), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Crawford, Marc (with Abe Osheroff and Howard Johnson), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Event: U.S., undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Event: U.S., undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Event: U.S., undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Event: U.S., undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Event: U.S., 1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Event: U.S., 1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Event: U.S., 1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Event: U.S., 1994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Event: U.S., 1995 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Event: U.S., 1997-04 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Event: U.S., 1997-04 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Event: U.S., Apr 1997 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Event: U.S., 1998-04 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Fisher, Harry: Book Signing, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Johnson, Howard (Stretch), undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - March: Barcelona, 1997-11 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - March: Against U.S. Blockade of Cuba, New York City, 1995-10 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - March: Washington, DC, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - March: Washington, DC, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Spain: Contact Sheets, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Spain: Demonstrations/Marches by Eric Levenson, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Spain: Jarama Battlefield, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Spain: Madrid, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Spain: Madrid, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Spain: Madrid Ceremony, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Spain: Madrid Ceremony, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Spain: Press Conference, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Spain: Truro, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Spain: Truro, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Barcelona, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Barcelona, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Barcelona, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Barcelona, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Barcelona, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Barcelona, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Barcelona, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Barcelona, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Barcelona, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Barcelona, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Madrid, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Madrid, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Madrid, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Madrid, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Madrid, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Madrid, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Madrid, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Madrid, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Seville, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Seville, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Seville, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Spain: Veterans Trip, Seville, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Village Voice Protest: By Barbara Smith, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Watson, Roach (Gravesite), 1987 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Yates, James, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Yates, James, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Series II: Negatives
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 1, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 6, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 7, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 10, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 11, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 12, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 13, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 14, 1995-04 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 15, 1997-04 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 16, 1997-04 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 17, 1998-04 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 18, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 21, 1995-10 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 22, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 23, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 24, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 26, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 27, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 28, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 29, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 30, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 31, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 32, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 33, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 35, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 38, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 39, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 1 Folder 40, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 2 Folder 1, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 2 Folder 2, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 2 Folder 3, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 2 Folder 4, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 2 Folder 5, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 2 Folder 6, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 2 Folder 7, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 2 Folder 8, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 2 Folder 9, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 2 Folder 10, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 2 Folder 11, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 2 Folder 13, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 2 Folder 14, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 2 Folder 15, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 2 Folder 16, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 2 Folder 17, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Negatives Corresponding to Box 2 Folder 18, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)